A Guide to John Henry Ingram's Poe Collection
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Part One: Letters, Manuscripts, Other Documents
  - SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, ALS to INGRAM, 1876 July 11 and 18.; [295]; 6 pp. (Box 5)
    Mrs. Whitman thinks that Poe's note on cowardice in "Marginalia" which Ingram wants to suppress is absurd but hardly "hateful." It was, she believes, intended as a play on words. "In all matters not affecting important truths," however, she is heartily in favor of suppressing whatever seems to an editor irrelevant or likely to injure the reputation of his subject. Caleb Fiske Harris is surprised that Poe's first "To Helen" was not included in Tamerlane. All of Ingram's discoveries about the order of Poe's prose articles, stories, and poems are intensely interesting to her. Eugene L. Didier thinks the long letter about Poe which Mrs. Whitman wrote to him at his request will have great weight in disproving scandals about him, if it is published exactly as she wrote it. Mrs. Whitman is sure that her treatment of the subject will interest Ingram and meet with his cordial approval. His article on Poe's early poems has been reprinted in the New York Daily Graphic sometime in June or July of 1876.
  - ELIZABETH OAKES SMITH, Hollywood, NC, APCS to SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, 1876 July 15.; [296] (Box 5)
    Enclosed in Item 299. Mrs. Oakes Smith denies that she wrote the story about Poe's having been beaten to death by the friend of a lady whom he had deceived and betrayed.
  - ANNIE RICHMOND, Lowell, MA, ALS to INGRAM, 1876 August 15.; [297]; 2 pp. (Box 5)
    Since receiving Ingram's letter in June, Mrs. Richmond has been trying to recover from William F. Gill the MS. of a sketch of Poe. She cannot let her letters from Poe out of her keeping, but if Ingram comes to see her she will place them at his disposal. She believes the letters to be without parallel in the annals of love and shrinks from allowing the purity of them to be revealed to other eyes, but for the sake of refuting the calumnies that have been heaped on Poe through jealousy and envy, she is willing that Ingram use them.
  - ANNIE RICHMOND, Lowell, MA, ALS to INGRAM, 1876 August 20.; [298]; 6 pp. (Box 5)
    Mrs. Richmond encloses copies of her sister Sarah Heywood's "Recollections of Poe" and Poe's letter of 23 November 1848, to Sarah Heywood. [For the text of Poe's letter see Letters, 2: 405-406].
  - SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, ALS to INGRAM, 1876 August 25.; [299]; 4 pp. (Box 5)
    Mrs. Whitman has received a copy of Ingram's article, "The Bibliography of Edgar Poe " in the London Athenaeum, 19 August 1876. After a silence of ten or twelve years, she has written to Elizabeth Oakes Smith to say that she has not hesitated to deny that Mrs. Oakes Smith was the author of a personal assault on Poe. Mrs. Oakes Smith has replied in a postcard and two "most kind" letters. William F. Gill has achieved notoriety by sliding down a ravine in the White Mountains. To Mrs. Whitman, Gill is like the "missing link" or the "Lost Pleiad."
  - ANNIE RICHMOND, Lowell, MA, ALS to INGRAM, 1876 September 27.; [300]; 2 pp. (Box 5)
    Mrs. Richmond encloses a "small portion" of her letters from Poe, trusting to Ingram's honor that neither the living nor the dead shall ever suffer in consequence. She will send to Ingram copies of pictures of Poe and Maria Clemm. She was unable to see Mrs. Clemm during her last illness, but would be glad to regain possession of Poe's letters to her which Mrs. Clemm had. Poe sent or gave to her MS. copies of "The Bells," "For Annie," and "A Dream Within a Dream."
  - ANNIE RICHMOND, Lowell, MA, ALS to INGRAM, 1876 October 3.; [301]; 3 pp. (Box 6)
    Mrs. Richmond has mailed a package containing letters from Poe and Maria Clemm as well as a photographs of both. Ingram may keep the pictures, and if this package reaches him safely, she will send more letters or copies. Poe told her little of his early history, but Mrs. Clemm cared to talk of nothing else when she had an attentive listener. Mrs. Richmond regrets that she cannot be certain about dates and names, but she is thankful to know that at last justice will be done to Poe's dear memory.
  - SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, ALS to INGRAM, 1876 October 19.; [302]; 6 pp. (Box 6)
    The "advisers" of Sara S. Rice want William D. O'Connor to modify some of the things he said [about Walt Whitman ] in the article he submitted for the Poe memorial volume. Annie Richmond's letters to Maria Clemm, which were passed on to Mrs. Whitman, convinced Mrs. Whitman of Mrs. Richmond's fidelity to Poe's memory, and Mrs. Whitman is glad to know that Ingram has received from Mrs. Richmond a gracious tribute to Poe's "genuine goodness of heart & character." Mentions: Eugene L. Didier's "Memoir" being scheduled to preface the Household Edition of Poe's poems; Ingram's saying that he has in his possession the MS. of Elizabeth Oakes Smith's paragraph about Poe's violent death; Robert T. P. Allen's article in Scribner's, November 1875, about Poe's having worked in a Baltimore brickyard in 1834; and William F. Gill's having written to Mrs. Whitman two letters within one week after a year's silence.
  - SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, ALS to INGRAM, 1876 November 14 and 20.; [303]; 14 pp. (Box 6)
    Poe told Mrs. Whitman of his intention to write a pendant to his "The Domain of Arnheim." The things Ingram writes to Mrs. Whitman about "Landor's Cottage" convinces her that Ingram was "destined" to the work which he is "so effectually performing." Stephane Mallarme wishes to dedicate to her his volume of translations of Poe's poems. She has related to Mallarme "all" that Poe said to her about "Ulalume." Her feeling now is that Poe's omitting of the closing stanza of "Ulalume" at her request was a mistake because the stanza "is necessary to the comprehension of the poem." Mrs. Whitman tells Ingram of Poe's reading of "Ulalume" to her in the Providence Athenaeum Library and then signing the bound volume of the American Whig Review, in which it had first appeared. William F. Gill informs Mrs. Whitman that he proposes to publish a volume on Poe, and Mrs. Whitman has insisted that Gill show her proofs of anything of hers that he uses or anything that he writes relating to her. Gill wanted William J. Widdleton to publish his things together with Eugene L. Didier's, but Didier would not consent. Mentions: Poe daguerreotypes and copies made from them, Mary Osborne, Ingram's obituary of John Neal, and Mary Gove Nichol's "Reminiscences of Poe."
  - ANNIE RICHMOND, Lowell, MA, ALS to INGRAM, 1876 November 21.; [304]; 3 pp. (Box 6)
    Only the intense desire to have full justice done to Poe's memory could have tempted Mrs. Richmond to put her correspondence with Poe in Ingram's hands, but she is certain he will not allow it to be made public. Her remaining letters from Poe are so personal and contain so few allusions "to matters that would interest" Ingram, she is not sure that copying them would be worthwhile, but if Ingram comes to America, she will place the originals in his hands. She is surprised to learn that her MS. copy of "The Bells" is not the original one, for Poe copied it while at her house and left her what she thought was the first copy. One very valuable letter of Poe's belonging to her was in Maria Clemm's possession.
  - SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, ALS to INGRAM, 1876 December 15.; [305]; 4 pp. (Box 6)
    The proofs of William F. Gill's volume on Poe are at hand and are a curious melange mostly of things heretofore published, the "profoundly interesting" exception being Sarah Heywood's "Recollections of Poe."
  - SARAH H. HEYWOOD, Lowell, MA, ALS to INGRAM, 1876 December 25.; [306]; 2 pp. (Box 6)
    Miss Heywood introduces Franklin E. Brown, who will hand Ingram a package containing an early edition of Poe's Tales of the Grotesque and Arabesque, 2 volumes, which were found in the trunk belonging to Poe that was forwarded to Maria Clemm at Lowell soon after his death.
  - SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, ALS to INGRAM, 1876 December 31.; [307]; 8 pp. (Box 6)
    Eugene L. Didier writes in his "Memoir" that Poe's mother had been twice married and that she and Poe's father died in the Richmond theater fire. Ingram is to be very careful not to allow Maria Clemm's letters, which have Mrs. Whitman's marginal comments, to pass into other hands. To her surprise, Mrs. Whitman's letter to Didier about Poe is printed as an "Introductory Letter" in his volume which she will send to Ingram if he wants it. Baltimoreans seem greatly pleased over Ingram's "Memoir" as he prepared it for the memorial volume which Sara S. Rice has edited. Mrs. Whitman urges Ingram to change the words "fierce flame" as describing the interest she first aroused in Poe because at that time Virginia Poe was still alive. "But there is nothing of earthly passion in the poem he sent me --is there?"
  - ANNIE RICHMOND, Lowell, MA, ALS on the back of an announcement of Poe's Stylus, April 1848., ca. 1876.; [308]; 1 p. (Box 6)
    Mrs. Richmond is willing to answer Ingram's questions about Poe and is thankful for the romance which found its way into the web and woof of her early life and for the sweet memories that brighten its present day.
  - SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, ALS to INGRAM, 1877 January 9.; [309]; 4 pp. (Box 6)
    Mrs. Whitman discusses Poe daguerreotypes and photographs taken from them. William F. Gill has been burned out; consequently, the publication of his biography of Poe will be delayed. Mrs. Whitman will send a copy of Eugene L. Didier's new biography of Poe to Ingram by the next day's steamer.
  - ANNIE RICHMOND, Lowell, MA, ALS to INGRAM, 1877 January 14.; [310]; 4 pp. (Box 6)
    Mrs. Richmond copies for Ingram Poe's letter to Sarah Helen Whitman of 25 January 1849 [Item 55]. She encloses a note from Charles Dickens' agent which had accompanied a sum of money sent to Maria Clemm by Dickens. "Mr. Poe as a Cryptographer" was written by Reverend Warren A. Cudworth of East Boston.
  - RICHARD GARNETT, British Museum, ALS to INGRAM, 1877 January 15.; [311]; 3 pp. (Box 6)
    A Boston Theatre advertisement in the Centinel, 18 April 1809, lists Mrs. Poe as playing Amelia in The Robbers and as Ella in James Kenney's Ella Rosenbery. This was the benefit night for the Poes. David Poe's part is not listed.
  - ANNIE RICHMOND, Lowell, MA, ALS to INGRAM, 1877 January 31.; [312]; 4 pp. (Box 6)
    Mrs. Richmond will search in Boston for a file of the Flag of Our Union and for a number of Graham's which Ingram needs. She sends all of the letters she received from Maria Clemm before Poe's death; Ingram need not return them. Two or three of Poe's letters to Mrs. Richmond are missing. When Mrs. Clemm visited Lowell she had access to them, and after she left they were missing. Later, Mrs. Clemm borrowed a letter that never was returned, though she said that she had sent it back. Mrs. Richmond met William F. Gill through a friend who had urged her to help him prepare a lecture on Poe, and when Gill went to Baltimore, he borrowed her MS. copy of "The Bells" so that he might read it there with more effect. She is enthusiastic about Ingram's work and is sure that it will be a complete and thorough vindication of that "dear and tenderly cherished name."
  - SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, ALS to INGRAM, 1877 February 2.; [313]; 6 pp. (Box 6)
    Mrs. Whitman compares "vraisemblance" in portraits, daguerreotypes, and photographs of Poe. She has heard nothing lately about William F. Gill's biography of Poe. Julian Hawthorne is incensed over George P. Lathrop's publication of Nathaniel Hawthorne's private journal. After Algernon Charles Swinburne's noble rebuke of Thomas Carlyle's barbarous and brutal policy, will Carlyle not wear sackcloth and ashes the rest of his dishonored days? Mrs. Whitman has at last received her copy of Stephane Mallarme's Le Corbeau but finds some of Edouard Manet's illustrations beyond the range of her appreciation.
  - ANNIE RICHMOND, Lowell, MA, ALS to INGRAM, 1877 February 5.; [314]; 3 pp. (Box 6)
    If Ingram wishes, Mrs. Richmond will cut an article on secret writing and two chapters of "Autography" for Ingram from bound volumes of Graham's for 1841 and 1842. She is unable to answer definitely many of Ingram's questions, for she did not comprehend the rare opportunities she had when Poe talked because wonder and admiration completely absorbed her. As he related them, the events of his life had a flavor of unreality, just like his stories.
  - ANNA BLACKWELL, Pas de Calais, ALS to INGRAM, 1877 February 12.; [315]; 4 pp. (Box 6)
    Miss Blackwell denies that Ingram could possibly have a copy of a letter written to her by Poe because she had never received one from him. She remembers that she visited the Poe s at Fordham in company with someone whose name she now does not recall to deliver a basket of delicacies suitable for an invalid and that Poe had returned that visit. She will not permit Ingram to use her name in connection with the letter or with anything he is writing about Poe. [For a complete text of Poe's letter to Miss Blackwell, written from Fordham on 14 June 1848, see Letters 2: 369-371. Anna Blackwell herself gave this letter to Sarah Helen Whitman. ]
  - SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, ALS to INGRAM, 1877 March 2.; [316]; 6 pp. (Box 6)
    All that Mrs. Whitman has written Ingram about Anna Blackwell she learned from the lady herself. It was Mary Gove Nichols who advised Anna Blackwell to board at the Poe cottage for a few weeks of country air and rest from her literary labors. After Miss Blackwell had given her Poe's letter, Mrs. Whitman gave it to the Hon. John Russell Bartlett of Providence for his valuable collection of autographs, and it was he who had allowed her to make the copy which she sent to Ingram. Mrs. Whitman is deeply wounded by the tone of Ingram's letter to her and by his disposition to cross-examine her testimony so peremptorily. She is not aware that Eugene L. Didier has ever spoken an unkind word about Ingram, and she wonders why they should be enemies.
  - SARA SIGOURNEY RICE, Baltimore, ALS to INGRAM, 1877 March 8.; [317]; 4 pp. (Box 6)
    The inclusion of Ingram's "noble" "Memoir" has rendered the Poe memorial volume an "angel of reparation."
  - ANNIE RICHMOND, Lowell, MA, ALS to INGRAM, 1877 March 13.; [318]; 6 pp. (Box 6)
    The files of the Flag of Our Union and some of Poe's MSS. were destroyed by fire in 1872 or 1873, but Mrs. Richmond knows where there is a collection of Graham's and Burton's Gentleman's Magazine, and if the numbers Ingram wants are among them they will be forwarded. The gossip connected with Poe and Sarah Helen Whitman, relayed from Providence by Mr. Richmond's family, came close to putting to an end her correspondence with Poe. Mrs. Richmond is sorry that William F. Gill ever crossed her path, and her sister, Sarah Heywood, will write Gill requesting that he not publish her recollections of Poe. Jane E. Locke was deeply in love with Poe. Since her death, Mrs. Richmond has destroyed a large package of her letters that Poe had sent to her, but she encloses one memento of Mrs. Locke. She has given Poe's MS. of "A Dream Within a Dream" to Mrs. Crane of East Boston, at the intercession of her pastor, Reverend Warren H. Cudworth.
  - SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, ALS to INGRAM, 1877 April 13.; [319]; 4 pp. (Box 6)
    Mrs. Whitman considers the review of Eugene L. Didier's "Memoir of Poe" in the London Athenaeum, 10 February 1877, an unprovoked assault upon herself. Ingram had said that he had lent her copy of the book to "a friend" who wrote the review. Mrs. Whitman considers the matter itself of little moment, but the animus of it is a rude shock to all her previous impressions of the young Englishman who had invoked her aid, had sought her confidence and criticism, and had hailed her as his "Providence." She and Ingram seem to have been like ships that meet on sea, then pass to meet no more.
  - EDWARD V. VALENTINE, Richmond, ALS to INGRAM, 1877 April 27.; [320]; 2 pp. (Box 6)
    Valentine encloses copies of the inscriptions on the gravestones of John Allan, Frances Allan, and Ann Moore Valentine which are in the Allan section of the Shockoe Hill Cemetery in Richmond.
  - ANNIE RICHMOND, Lowell, MA, ALS to INGRAM, 1877 May 27.; [321]; 4 pp. (Box 6)
    William F. Gill has taken her to task for helping Ingram and has asked her to request Ingram not to use Sarah Heywood's "Recollections of Poe" without letting him know that Gill desires that he not do so. Maria Clemm always spoke in strong terms of denunciation about the treatment Edgar received from the Allan family, but Mrs. Richmond thinks that Mrs. Clemm either did not know or would not reveal the real truths of the matter. She does not want to meet Sarah Helen Whitman but would like to meet Sarah Elmira Royster Shelton and Marie Louise Shew Houghton, and she shrinks from Sarah Anna Lewis. [Item 18 is enclosed.]
  - SARAH H. HEYWOOD, Lowell, MA, ALS to INGRAM, 1877 July 6.; [322]; 4 pp. (Box 6)
    Miss Heywood gives Ingram permission to us her "Recollections of Poe" in any way he pleases and wishes the sketch had gone into other hands because she has no confidence in William F. Gill's scholarly ability or literary taste; she allowed Gill to have it only because she thought it might help him write a better lecture on Poe. She encloses a newsclipping copy of a sonnet addressed to Annie Richmond by Benjamin West Ball.
  - H. B. W. [" HELEN BULLOCK WEBSTER, " i.e., GEORGE W. EVELETH ], "Nemonia, U. S.," letter to the Editor of Scribner's Monthly, 1877 October 7.; [323]; Copy by Eveleth. 3 pp. (Box 6)
    Enclosed in Item 340. Eveleth questions a notice of William F. Gill's biography of Poe reporting in Scribner's that it has been well ascertained that Poe's intoxication was a thing caused by even the smallest quantity of wine and took the form of strange and highly intellectual but deranged orations on abstruse subjects. Eveleth wants to know how this has been ascertained. He points out that even Rufus Griswold did not charge Poe with habitual use of intoxicants and that N. P. Willis, George R. Graham, Frances S. Osgood, and Sarah Helen Whitman have said that they never discovered signs of strong drink in Poe. Why do the New York literati with whom Poe was personally acquainted not come forward to answer these questions about his drinking? Who has reported these "deranged orations"? Were they set down by Poe or by anyone for him? Are they part, or all, of his printed volumes? If so, the disorder assumed is nowhere manifest in the contents. Eveleth does not believe the stories of Poe's common drunkenness or of the crazing power of a drop of wine.
  - ANNIE RICHMOND, Lowell, MA, ALS to INGRAM, 1877 October 8.; [324]; 4 pp. (Box 6)
    William F. Gill has shown himself to be an unscrupulous mountebank by using her sister Sarah Heywood's recollections of Poe in his volume after she had written him that she wanted to use her paper for an article of her own. Mrs. Richmond has reason to believe that at least one favorable review of Gill's biography was written for a consideration. She never liked Gill, found his personality disagreeable, but when Ingram wrote to her she felt immediately that he "ought to know," that he "must know," the things she knew about Poe. Poe told her that Flag of Our Union was a miserable paper but that the editors paid well. Maria Clemm had promised to leave to her all of her papers and letters. William Rouse has Edgar Poe's letter to William E. Burton of 1 June 1840 [Item 18].
  - ANNIE RICHMOND, Lowell, MA, ALS to INGRAM, 1877 November 25.; [325]; 4 pp. (Box 6)
    William F. Gill's publishing of extracts from letters of Poe to Mrs. Richmond is incomprehensible to her because Gill had only heard her read aloud portions of them some six or seven years earlier and the letters have never been out of her keeping. Bound volumes of Graham's for 1843, 1846, and 1848 can be bought in Boston for $6 for all three. Is that too much? Mrs. Richmond thinks that Gill's scandalous attack on Ingram in the Boston Sunday Herald for 18 November is beneath Ingram's notice. She is sorry that Marie Louise Shew Houghton has died. Elizabeth F. Ellet was once Poe's friend, but he said that she exasperated him beyond forgiveness. Poe made remarks about Mrs. Ellet and one or two other literary ladies in a letter to Mrs. Richmond, and for that reason, she suspects, Maria Clemm wanted to get possession of it.
  - SARAH H. HEYWOOD, Lowell, MA, ALS to INGRAM, 1877 December 24.; [326]; 3 pp. (Box 6)
    Although often urged to do so, Annie Richmond has never sat for a photograph. Perhaps Ingram's request may prevail.
  - ANNIE RICHMOND, Lowell, MA, ALS to INGRAM, 1877 December 30.; [327]; 2 pp. (Box 6)
    Mrs. Richmond feels that she is in Ingram's power since she has sent to him her letters from Poe, but she trusts him implicitly and is confident that she will never have cause for regret. She met William F. Gill at the Old South Fair and shrank from him as if he had been a reptile. If she can make up her mind to sit for a photograph, Ingram shall have one.
  - ANNIE RICHMOND, Lowell, MA, ALS to INGRAM, 1878 January 8.; [328]; 3 pp. (Box 6)
    Mrs. Richmond's MSS. of "The Bells" and "A Dream Within a Dream" have been lost by the photographer who was to make copies of them for Ingram.
  - SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, ALS to INGRAM, 1878 January 16.; [329]; 4 pp. (Box 6)
    If Ingram's words in some of his letters caused Mrs. Whitman pain during the past eventful year, the "via dolorosa" which she has "of late" been called to tread has "effaced all minor sorrows, and regrets." She remembers only the happiness she felt in his earlier sympathy and friendship. She is now in the beautiful home of the Dailey's, surrounded by her own "household goods," save those that fell under the auctioneer's hammer.
  - ANNIE RICHMOND, Lowell, MA, ALS to INGRAM, 1878 February 5.; [330]; 4 pp. (Box 6)
    The lost MSS. of "The Bells" and "A Dream Within a Dream" have been found among the dead letters in the local post office! "A Dream Within a Dream" was sent to her by Poe in "a sort of farewell letter" that is now lost; later Poe made additions to the poem and published it in the Flag of Our Union. For Poe's sake, Mrs. Richmond has placed her correspondence and herself willingly and completely in Ingram's hands, asking only that he use the correspondence as he would wish another to use it if his wife or his sister were in her position. She feels acutely the delicacy of her relationship with Poe and knows well what nine out of ten people would make of it, given the opportunity Ingram has.
  - ANNIE RICHMOND, Lowell, MA, ALS to INGRAM, 1878 February 12.; [331]; 5 pp. (Box 6)
    Poe's affection for Mrs. Richmond is the most precious memory her heart holds, and she has always spoken of him as an acquaintance and not as a friend because the world could not understand their friendship. She is thankful that William F. Gill did not get the MS. of "A Dream Within a Dream" and that Ingram will have the privilege of printing it in its original form. She encloses a copy of the MS. of "The Bells."
  - THOMAS G. CLARKE, Richmond, ALS to EDWARD V. VALENTINE, 1878 February.; [332]; 1 p. (Box 6)
    Enclosed in Item 339. Clarke was present when Poe easily swam five miles in the James River and heard him read "The Raven" in the Concert Room of the Exchange Hotel.
  - SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, ALS to INGRAM, 1878 March 9.; [333]; Written on both sides of a small envelope. (Box 6)
    Mrs. Whitman has much to say to Ingram, much to ask. She is preparing something to leave, after her "dematerialization," to those who love her. Ingram's sorrow is a sorrow to her, always. "Benedicte."